<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--<?xml-model href="../schema/kellyschema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>-->
<chtext>
    <meta>
        <title>
            Chapter 8 Excerpt
        </title>
        <chapterinfo xml:id="8"> </chapterinfo>
    </meta>
    <body>
        <p>
            <q speaker="Sherlock">"I have no wish to make a mystery of him, to you, anyway. But you
                must have formed your own opinion. Now, do consider the data. <adj_per desc="orient"
                    cat="prim"> Diminutive footmarks, toes never fettered by boots, naked feet,
                    stone-headed wooden mace, great agility, </adj_per><adj_obj desc="orient"
                    cat="prim">small poisoned darts.</adj_obj> What do you make of all this?"</q>
        </p>
        <p>
            <q speaker="Watson"><adj_per desc="orient" cat="prim">"A savage!"</adj_per></q> I
            exclaimed. <q speaker="Watson">"Perhaps one of those Indians who were the associates of
                Jonathan Small."</q>
        </p>
        <p>
            <q speaker="Sherlock">"Hardly that,"</q> said he. <q speaker="Sherlock">"When first I saw <adj_obj desc="orient"
                    cat="prim">signs of strange weapons</adj_obj> I was inclined to think so; but
                the remarkable character of the footmarks caused me to reconsider my views. Some of
                the inhabitants of the <loc>Indian Peninsula</loc> are <adj_per desc="orient"
                    cat="prim">small men</adj_per>, but none could have left such marks as that.
                    <adj_per desc="orient" cat="none">The Hindoo proper has long and thin
                    feet</adj_per>. <adj_per desc="orient" cat="none">The sandal-wearing Mohammedan
                    has the great toe well separated from the others</adj_per>, <adj_ob
                    desc="orient" cat="prim">because the thong is commonly passed between</adj_ob>.
                    <adj_ob desc="orient" cat="prim">These little darts</adj_ob>, too, could only be
                shot in one way. They are from a<adj_ob desc="orient" cat="prim">blow-pipe</adj_ob>.
                Now, then, where are we to find our <adj_per desc="orient" cat="prim"
                    >savage</adj_per>?"</q>
        </p>
        <p>
            <q speaker="Watson"><loc>"South American</loc>," I hazarded.</q>
        </p>
        <p>
            <narr>He stretched his hand up, and took down a bulky volume from the shelf.</narr>
            <q speaker="Sherlock">"This is the first volume of a gazetteer which is now being
                published. It may be looked upon as the very latest authority. What have we here?
                    <subq type="Gazetteer"><loc>'Andaman Islands, situated 340 miles to the
                        north of Sumatra, in the Bay of Bengal.'</loc></subq> Hum! hum! What's
                all this? <subq type="Gazetteer">Moist climate, coral reefs, sharks, Port Blair,
                    convict-barracks, <loc>Rutland Island</loc>, cottonwoods.'</subq> ”Ah, here
                we are. <subq type="Gazetteer"><adj_per desc="orient" cat="prim">'The aborigines
                        of the <loc>Andaman Islands</loc> may perhaps claim the distinction of being
                        the smallest race upon this earth</adj_per>, though some anthropologists
                    prefer the Bushmen of Africa, the Digger Indians of America, and the Terra del
                    Fuegians. <adj_per desc="orient" cat="prim">The average height is rather below
                        four feet, although many full-grown adults may be found who are very much
                        smaller than this</adj_per>. They are a <adj_per desc="orient" cat="neg"
                        >fierce, morose, and intractable people</adj_per>, <adj_per desc="orient"
                        cat="pos">though capable of forming most devoted friendships when their
                        confidence has once been gained</adj_per>. '</subq> Mark that, Watson.
                Now, then, listen to this. <subq type="Gazetteer"><adj_per desc="orient"
                        cat="neg">'They are naturally hideous, having large, misshapen heads, small,
                        fierce eyes, and distorted features</adj_per>. <adj_per desc="orient"
                        cat="none">Their feet and hands, however, are remarkably small</adj_per>.
                        <adj_per desc="orient" cat="prim">So intractable and fierce are
                        they</adj_per> that all the efforts of the British official have failed to
                    win them over in any degree. They have always been a <adj_per desc="orient"
                        cat="prim">terror to shipwrecked crews</adj_per>, <vb type="orient"
                        cat="viol">braining the survivors</vb> with their <adj_obj desc="orient"
                        cat="prim">stone-headed clubs</adj_obj>, or <vb type="orient" cat="viol"
                        >shooting them</vb> with their <adj_obj desc="orient" cat="prim">poisoned
                        arrows</adj_obj>. These massacres are <adv_per desc="orient" cat="prim"
                        >invariably concluded by a cannibal feast</adv_per>.'</subq><adj_per
                    desc="orient" cat="neg">Nice, amiable people</adj_per>, Watson! If this fellow
                had been left to his own unaided devices <adv_per type="orient" cat="prim">this
                    affair might have taken an even more ghastly turn</adv_per>. I fancy that, even
                as it is, Jonathan Small would give a good deal not to have employed him."</q>
        </p>
        <p>
            <q speaker="Watson">"But how came he to have so singular a companion?"</q>
        </p>
        <p>
            <q speaker="Sherlock">"Ah, that is more than I can tell. Since, however, we had already
                determined that Small had come from the <loc>Andamans</loc>, it is not so very
                wonderful that this <adj_per desc="orient" cat="prim">islander</adj_per> should be
                with him. No doubt we shall know all about it in time. Look here, Watson; you look
                regularly done. Lie down there on the sofa, and see if I can put you to sleep."</q>
        </p>
        <p>
            <narr>He took up his violin from the corner, and as I stretched myself out he began to play
            some low, dreamy, melodious air, his own, no doubt, for he had a remarkable gift for
            improvisation. I have a vague remembrance of his gaunt limbs, his earnest face, and the
            rise and fall of his bow. Then I seemed to be floated peacefully away upon a soft sea of
            sound, until I found myself in dream-land, with the sweet face of Mary Morstan looking
            down upon me.</narr>
        </p>
    </body>
</chtext>
