<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book>
    <title>The SIgn of the Four</title>
<chapter>Chapter 8</chapter> 
 <p><dialogue><speaker name="Sherlock" class="upper">I have no wish to make a mystery of him,—to you, anyway. But you must have formed your own opinion
     Now, do consider the data. <native_desc type="orientneg" cast="none" size="small">Diminutive footmarks</native_desc>, <native_desc type="orientneg" cast="primitive">toes never
         fettered by boots</native_desc>, <native_desc type="orientneg" cast="primitive">naked feet</native_desc>, stone-headed wooden mace, <native_desc type="orientpos">great agility</native_desc>, 
     <object_desc type="orientprim">small poisoned darts</object_desc>. What do you make of all this?"</speaker></dialogue></p>

<p><dialogue><speaker name ="Watson" class="upper"><native_desc type="orientneg" cast="primitive">A savage!"</native_desc></speaker></dialogue> I exclaimed. 
    <dialogue><speaker name="Watson" class="upper">Perhaps one of those Indians who were the associates of Jonathan Small."</speaker></dialogue></p>

<p><dialogue><speaker name="Sherlock" class="upper">"Hardly that," </speaker>said he. <speaker type="Sherlock" class="upper">When first I saw signs of 
    <object_desc type="orientprim" category="diffneg">strange weapons</object_desc> I was inclined to think so; but the >remarkable
        character of the footmarks caused me to reconsider my views. Some of the inhabitants of the Indian Peninsula are <native_desc type="orientneg">small men</native_desc>,
but none could have left such marks as that. The Hindoo proper has <native_desc type="orientneut" cast="none" relig="Hindu">long and thin feet</native_desc>. The
    <object_desc type="orientneut" category="diffneut">sandal-wearing</object_desc> <native_desc type="orientneut" cast="none" relig="Muslim">Mohammedan </native_desc>has the 
    <native_desc type="orientneut" cast="none" relig="muslim"> great toe well separated from the others</native_desc>, because the thong is commonly passed
between. These <object_desc tytpe="orientprim" category="diffneg">little darts</object_desc>, too, could only be shot in one way. They are from a
    <object_desc type="orientprim" category="diffneut">blow-pipe</object_desc>. Now, then, where are we to find our <native_desc type="orientneg" cast="primitive">savage?"
</native_desc></speaker></dialogue></p>

    <p><dialogue><speaker name="Watson" class="upper">"South American," </speaker></dialogue>I hazarded.</p>

<p>He stretched his hand up, and took down a bulky volume from the shelf.<dialogue><speaker type="Sherlock" class="upper">This is the first volume of a gazetteer 
    which is now being published. It may be looked upon as the very latest authority. What have we here? 'Andaman Islands, situated 340 miles to the north of Sumatra, 
    in the Bay of Bengal.' Hum! hum! What's all this? Moist climate, coral reefs, sharks, Port Blair, convict-barracks, Rutland Island, cottonwoods—Ah, here we are.
'<native_desc type="orientneg" cast="primitive" size="small">The aborigines of the Andaman Islands may perhaps claim the distinction of being the smallest race upon this earth</native_desc>
    , though some anthropologists prefer the Bushmen of Africa, the Digger Indians of America, and the Terra del Fuegians. <native_desc type="orientneut" size="small">The average height is 
        rather below four feet, although many full-grown adults may be found who are very much smaller than this</native_desc>.
    <native_desc type="oreintneg" cast="primitive" character="neg">They are a fierce, morose, and intractable people</native_desc>,<native_desc type="orientpos" character="pos">
     though capable of forming most devoted friendships when their confidence has once been gained</native_desc>.' Mark that, Watson. Now, then, listen to this.
    '<native_desc type="orientneg" body="ugly" cast="primitive">They are naturally hideous, having large, misshapen heads, small, fierce eyes, and distorted features</native_desc>.
   <native_desc type="orientneg" body="small"> Their feet and hands, however, are remarkably small</native_desc>. So <native_desc type="orientneg" character="neg">
       intractable and fierce</native_desc> are they that all the efforts of the British official have failed to win them over in any degree. <native_desc type="orientprim" character="neg" custom="violent">
     They have always been a terror to shipwrecked crews, braining the survivors</native_desc> with their <object_desc type="orientprim">stone-headed clubs</object_desc>, 
    or shooting them with their <object_desc type="orientprim" category="diffneg"> poisoned arrows</object_desc>. 
    <native_desc type="orientneg" cast="primitive" character="neg" custom="violent">These massacres are invariably concluded by a cannibal feast.'</native_desc>
    Nice, amiable people, Watson! If <native_desc type="orientneg" cast="primitive" custom="violent" character="neg">this fellow </native_desc>had been left to his 
    own unaided devices this affair might have taken an even more ghastly turn. I fancy that, even as it is, Jonathan Small would give a good deal not to have employed him."</speaker></dialogue></p>

<p><dialogue><speaker type="Watson" class="upper">But how came he to have so singular a companion?"</speaker></dialogue></p>

<p><dialogue><speaker type="Sherlock" class="upper">Ah, that is more than I can tell. Since, however, we had already determined that Small had come from the Andamans,
    it is not so very wonderful that this <native_desc type="orientneut">islander</native_desc> should be with him. No doubt we shall know
    all about it in time. Look here, Watson; you look regularly done. Lie down there on the sofa, see if I can put you to sleep."</speaker></dialogue></p>

<p>He took up his violin from the corner, and as I stretched myself out he began to play some low, dreamy, melodious air,—his own, no doubt, for he had a 
remarkable gift for improvisation. I have a vague remembrance of his gaunt limbs, his earnest face, and the rise and fall of his bow. Then I seemed to be 
floated peacefully away upon a soft sea of sound, until I found myself in dream-land, with the sweet face of Mary Morstan looking down upon me.</p>

</book>